Imagine you're a project manager and you
कल्पना करें कि आप एक प्रोजेक्ट मैनेजर हैं और आपको
need to coordinate with teams that speak
अलग-अलग भाषा बोलने वाली टीमों के साथ
different different languages with
उनके काम के संबंध में समन्वय करना है
respect to their work. Now imagine having
अब कल्पना करें कि आपके पास एक यूनिवर्सल ट्रांसलेटर है
a universal translator that lets you say,
जो आपको सादी अंग्रेजी में कहने देता है,
create a user dashboard in plain English
एक यूजर डैशबोर्ड बनाएं
and it automatically translates your
और यह आपकी रिक्वेस्ट को हर टीम की
request into each team's specialized
विशेषज्ञ भाषा में अपने आप
language. Without this translator, you
ट्रांसलेट कर देता है। इस ट्रांसलेटर के बिना
need to learn four different technical
आपको चार अलग-अलग तकनीकी
languages. This is what Model Context
भाषाएं सीखनी पड़ेंगी। यही है Model Context
Protocol or MCP is all about. With MCP,
Protocol या MCP का मतलब। MCP के साथ
you speak human language once and it
आप एक बार इंसानी भाषा बोलते हैं और यह
handles all the technical. Technical
सारा तकनीकी काम संभाल लेता है।
translation automatically. So basically
तकनीकी ट्रांसलेशन अपने आप हो जाती है।
MCP standardizes this translation layer
तो बेसिकली MCP इस ट्रांसलेशन लेयर को
so AI agents or LLMS can seamlessly talk
स्टैंडर्डाइज़ करता है ताकि AI एजेंट्स या LLMs
to databases, APIs, cloud services
डेटाबेस, APIs, क्लाउड सर्विसेज
and any other system without developers
और किसी भी अन्य सिस्टम से आसानी से बात कर सकें
having to build custom integrations for
बिना डेवलपर्स को हर एक के लिए
each one of them.
कस्टम इंटीग्रेशन बनाने की जरूरत के।